<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>ANotes - Books</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/feeds/books.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://adamnovotny.com/</id><updated>2021-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Benjamin Franklin by Walter Isaacson</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/benjamin-franklin-by-walter-isaacson.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2021-01-03:/blog/benjamin-franklin-by-walter-isaacson.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Franklin was in many ways an excellent role model for future generations of his new nation: a marketing expert, practical engineer, and a skilled negotiator with sense for compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*8pd7aWqA7IK2ZqTKBYJFlQ.jpeg.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*8pd7aWqA7IK2ZqTKBYJFlQ.jpeg.png" alt="Book cover: Benjamin Franklin by Walter Isaacson" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Franklin was a printer by training and later a newspaper publisher. Many newspaper articles were written using pseudonyms and newspapers …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Franklin was in many ways an excellent role model for future generations of his new nation: a marketing expert, practical engineer, and a skilled negotiator with sense for compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*8pd7aWqA7IK2ZqTKBYJFlQ.jpeg.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*8pd7aWqA7IK2ZqTKBYJFlQ.jpeg.png" alt="Book cover: Benjamin Franklin by Walter Isaacson" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Franklin was a printer by training and later a newspaper publisher. Many newspaper articles were written using pseudonyms and newspapers arguably read as modern social media. Therefore it is not surprising that Franklin was considered the most &lt;a href="https://www.mountvernon.org/library/digitalhistory/digital-encyclopedia/article/benjamin-franklin/" target="_blank"&gt;admired and famous founding father&lt;/a&gt; by some&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Retired from business in 1748 to focus on public service full time. He was often direct when speaking about politicians: “He wished to please everybody, and having little to give, he gave expectations”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;He established many public institutions including libraries and what we know today as the University of Pennsylvania&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The only man to sign the key documents codifying the creation of the United States: Declaration of Independence, the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Paris_(1783)" target="_blank"&gt;Treaty of Paris&lt;/a&gt;, and the Constitution&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Franklin spent many years living in Europe. He moved to London for 2 years as a &lt;a href="https://www.ushistory.org/franklin/info/timeline.htm" target="_blank"&gt;young printer in 1724&lt;/a&gt; and then as a US representative during the struggle for &lt;a href="https://www.ushistory.org/franklin/info/timeline2.htm" target="_blank"&gt;independence starting in 1757&lt;/a&gt;. In 1776 he moved to France to represent US interests with its key ally&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Perhaps the most interesting aspect of Franklin’s character was his ability to change his mind and convince others of his newly conflicting opinions. Franklin initially supported the Stamp Act of 1765, by which the British Parliament levied a new tax on British colonies. When Franklin learned of strong opposition in America he changed his views&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Franklin was not a theoretical thinker who generated his best work purely by thinking deeply &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/einstein-by-walter-isaacson.html" target="_blank"&gt;the way Einstein did&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, he had an excellent engineering mind that allowed him to connect the dots. He connected both &lt;a href="https://www.amphilsoc.org/about" target="_blank"&gt;people&lt;/a&gt; and ideas to create &lt;a href="https://www.fi.edu/benjamin-franklin/inventions" target="_blank"&gt;inventions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More about me: &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Einstein by Walter Isaacson</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/einstein-by-walter-isaacson.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-12-03:/blog/einstein-by-walter-isaacson.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Walter Isaacson dedicates most of the book to describing Einstein’s life, politics and the nature of his creativity. The fact that he spends much less time focusing on physics is perhaps not surprising given his target audience. This differs from similar books such as Robert Oppenheimer by Ray Monk …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Walter Isaacson dedicates most of the book to describing Einstein’s life, politics and the nature of his creativity. The fact that he spends much less time focusing on physics is perhaps not surprising given his target audience. This differs from similar books such as Robert Oppenheimer by Ray Monk or American Prometheus by Bird and Sherwin where physics plays a larger role. Below is list of fascinating ideas from Isaacson’s depiction of Einstein’s life:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*wHZ0bWo4YaLS_-het6t7oA.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*wHZ0bWo4YaLS_-het6t7oA.png.png" alt="Einstein by Walter Isaacson book cover" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Einstein did his best work when working as a patent examiner outside of academia. In fact, he failed to get a job in academia for a long time&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Folklore describing Einstein as a bad student isn’t true. Einstein was nonconformist and questioned educational methods but school never challenged him intellectually: “The value of a college education is not the learning of many facts but the training of the mind to think … A society’s competitive advantage will come not from how well its schools teach the multiplication and periodic tables, but from how well they stimulate imagination and creativity.”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;He was a citizen of 3 countries: Germany, Switzerland, USA but spent the second part of his life denouncing Germany. He hated nationalism and conflict&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Love/hate relationship with politics. As a Jew forced to leave Germany due to safety concerns, Einstein was naturally involved in public life. However, he also acknowledged the futility of such efforts: “Politics is for the present, while our equations are for eternity.”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rather than trying to explain physics, Isaacson avoided the risk by relying of Einstein’s contemporaries making the field sound too complex. Weizmann, the president of the World Zionist Organization, said the following about his time spent with Einstein: “During the [Atlantic] crossing, Einstein explained his theory [of relativity] to me every day, and by the time we arrived I was fully convinced that he really understands it.”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Einstein helped to spearhead the development of the Atom bomb. After the war he became a very strong opponent: “I do not know how the Third World War will be fought, but I can tell you what they will use in the Fourth — rocks”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More about me: &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Skin in the Game by Nassim Nicholas Taleb</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/skin-in-the-game-by-nassim-nicholas-taleb.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-10-04:/blog/skin-in-the-game-by-nassim-nicholas-taleb.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Skin in the Game is a curious collection of anecdotes that has to make everyone question the fairness of modern society. A short subset of interesting thoughts is below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*STVayKpah-JBAsfYqGfYtQ.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*STVayKpah-JBAsfYqGfYtQ.png.png" alt="Skin in the Game by Nassim Nicholas Taleb" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bureaucracy is a construction by which a person is conveniently separated from the consequences of their actions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;You will never fully …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Skin in the Game is a curious collection of anecdotes that has to make everyone question the fairness of modern society. A short subset of interesting thoughts is below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*STVayKpah-JBAsfYqGfYtQ.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*STVayKpah-JBAsfYqGfYtQ.png.png" alt="Skin in the Game by Nassim Nicholas Taleb" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bureaucracy is a construction by which a person is conveniently separated from the consequences of their actions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;You will never fully convince someone that he is wrong; only reality can. The curse of modernity is that we are increasingly populated by a class of people who are better at explaining than understanding … or better at explaining than doing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hammurabi’s code: If a builder builds a house and the house collapses and causes the death of the owner of the hours — the builder shall be put to death&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Skin in the game vs. no skin in the game. Bureaucrats vs citizens. Consultants vs businessmen. Executives vs Entrepreneurs. Copy editors vs writers. Journalists vs speculators&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Journalists should talk about what they own (stocks). Instead under the promise of impartiality, they talk about what they don’t own and therefore most likely don’t understand&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Society doesn’t move by consensus: only a few motivated people are enough to disproportionately move the needle&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ronald Coase: An employee is - by design - more valuable inside a firm than outside of it; that is, more valuable to the employer than the marketplace&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Only time validates expertise. The longer an idea has been around without being falsified, the longer its future expectancy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Time-tested ideas: cognitive dissonance (people rationalize inconsistent beliefs), loss aversion, negative advice (we know the wrong better than the right), skin in the game, antifragility, time discounting, madness of crowds, less is more, overconfidence, the Paradox of Progress&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hire, conditionally on an equal set of skills, the person with the least label-oriented education. The person had to overcome more hurdles&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Economic insecurity in journalism means that journalists have to produce the most popular opinion to sell their product to the crowds. In business, the opposite is true and following the crowd is penalized&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bible: “Be careful not to practice your righteousness in front of others to be seen by them. If you do, you will have no reward from your Father in heaven. So when you give to the needy, do not announce it with trumpets, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and on the streets, to be honored by others”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mathematicians think in objects and relations, jurists and legal thinkers in constructs, logicians in maximally abstract operators, and … fools in words&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Atheistic Soviet Communism: all-embracing control over all of human activity and thought, which makes discussions about whether religion or atheistic regimes are more murderous lacking in pertinence, precision, and realism&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ergodicity, ruin: play Russian roulette with $1M payout. The average return is 5/6 * $1M = $833k according to classical cost/benefit analysis. However, continue playing and you end up in the cemetery. The expected return is not computable&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About me: &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Everything Explained for the Professional Pilot by Richie Lengel</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/everything-explained-for-the-professional-pilot-by-richie-lengel.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-09-19:/blog/everything-explained-for-the-professional-pilot-by-richie-lengel.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;While summarizing this book isn’t useful due to its technical nature, below is a small subset of fun facts I came across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*lskc82ZtyUHR9VrR7Vz0Yg.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*lskc82ZtyUHR9VrR7Vz0Yg.png.png" alt="Everything Explained for the Professional Pilot by Richie Lengel book cover" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;GPS calculates position based on precise signals received from satellites. How precise? Being 1/1000 of a second off results in a 186-mile error in location. Main …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While summarizing this book isn’t useful due to its technical nature, below is a small subset of fun facts I came across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*lskc82ZtyUHR9VrR7Vz0Yg.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*lskc82ZtyUHR9VrR7Vz0Yg.png.png" alt="Everything Explained for the Professional Pilot by Richie Lengel book cover" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;GPS calculates position based on precise signals received from satellites. How precise? Being 1/1000 of a second off results in a 186-mile error in location. Main GPS system has 24 satellites, 4 of which must reach device at a time to calculate 3D position + time. They orbit Earth at an altitude of 11k miles twice a day&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Frequency ranges: Broadcast radio 535–1,605 kHz (wavelength 560–187m). Communications, VOR, marker beacons 30–300MHz (wavelength=10–1m). Transponder, radar, glidescope, GPS 300–3,000 MHz (wavelength 100–10cm)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Indicated altitude may not reflect actual altitude: if the air is colder below the aircraft, the (unadjusted) altimeter reads higher than true altitude (aircraft is lower than indicated)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Watt vs kW vs hp: light bulb wattage is the amount of work required to light the bulb for one hour; 1000 watts = 1 kW = 1.3 hp; one hp could keep a 75-watt bulb lit for about an hour&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Visibility at sea level on a clear day is about 3 SM. At 5,000 ft, visibility is about 90 miles. Earth’s curvature is visible at 50k feet where the horizon is more than 260 miles away&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About me: &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Something Deeply Hidden by Sean Carroll</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/something-deeply-hidden-by-sean-carroll.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-09-12:/blog/something-deeply-hidden-by-sean-carroll.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sean Carroll attempts to reconcile quantum mechanics with Einstein’s theory of relativity, something that physics conveniently ignores. There is a plethora of similar attempts such as Geometric Unity &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z7rd04KzLcg&amp;" target="_blank"&gt;presented&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Weinstein. Carroll’s book is very readable even for physics enthusiasts like myself who lack formal education in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sean Carroll attempts to reconcile quantum mechanics with Einstein’s theory of relativity, something that physics conveniently ignores. There is a plethora of similar attempts such as Geometric Unity &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z7rd04KzLcg&amp;" target="_blank"&gt;presented&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Weinstein. Carroll’s book is very readable even for physics enthusiasts like myself who lack formal education in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*FAA4W1jklc-8VM9GkjZk6Q.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*FAA4W1jklc-8VM9GkjZk6Q.png.png" alt="Something Deeply Hidden: Quantum Worlds and the Emergence of Spacetime Hardcover by Sean Carroll" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_probability" target="_blank"&gt;Quantum probability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schr%C3%B6dinger_equation" target="_blank"&gt;Schrödinger equation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_superposition" target="_blank"&gt;Superposition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Many-worlds_interpretation" target="_blank"&gt;Many-Worlds theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electromagnetic_field" target="_blank"&gt;Electromagnetic field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_constant" target="_blank"&gt;Planck constant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncertainty_principle" target="_blank"&gt;Uncertainty principle, Heisenberg’s uncertainty principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quantum notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Qubits: systems with two possible measurement outcomes. A classical “bit” has just two possible values, 0 and 1. The state of qubit is a superposition of two possibilities (e.g. spin up and down), each weighted by a complex number&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Entanglement arises because there is just one wave function for the entire universe, not separate wave functions for each component of the it&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Decoherence is a situation when macroscopic objects become entangled with the environment. Decoherence causes the wave function to split into multiple worlds&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“It makes no sense to wonder which branch I will end up in. Both of them have every right to think of themselves as me.” In Many-Worlds, the life-span of a person should be thought of as a branching tree&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;How many splittings have occured? Assume 10^(88) particules in the universe, each splits the wave function in two a million times per second, and we have 10^(18) seconds since the Big Bang: 10^(88) * 10^(6) * 10^(18) = 10^(112) splittings and 2^(10^(112)) branches&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Special relativity (1905): everyone measures light to travel at the same speed in vacuum. Since there is no absolute frame of motion, time and space are relative&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Consequences of General relativity: expansion of the universe and black holes. Special relativity is a framework, general relativity is a specific theory&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hawking: black holes emit particles into space. Those particles carry energy away from black holes. Black holes have entropy: where does the information go when black holes form and then evaporate?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;About me: &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Genome by A.G. Riddle</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/genome-by-a-g-riddle.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-08-16:/blog/genome-by-a-g-riddle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Genome is fascinating science fiction book focused on what could be hidden in human Genome. &lt;a href="https://www.agriddle.com/Genome" target="_blank"&gt;The book’s website&lt;/a&gt; has an interesting section explaining which of main themes are fact vs fiction. Below is a selection of 3 facts I found interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*eC-9aFUEdybt6i_MCKxQ2Q.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*eC-9aFUEdybt6i_MCKxQ2Q.png.png" alt="Genome by A.G. Riddle book cover" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Icebreaker&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exploratory ship at the beginning of …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Genome is fascinating science fiction book focused on what could be hidden in human Genome. &lt;a href="https://www.agriddle.com/Genome" target="_blank"&gt;The book’s website&lt;/a&gt; has an interesting section explaining which of main themes are fact vs fiction. Below is a selection of 3 facts I found interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*eC-9aFUEdybt6i_MCKxQ2Q.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*eC-9aFUEdybt6i_MCKxQ2Q.png.png" alt="Genome by A.G. Riddle book cover" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Icebreaker&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exploratory ship at the beginning of the book of based on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_22220_icebreaker" target="_blank"&gt;Russian Project 22220&lt;/a&gt;, the largest nuclear-powered icebreaker designed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Quaternary Extinction Event&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Quaternary extinction was a mass die-off of large animals that occurred during the transition from the Pleistocene to the Holocene epoch (13,000 BCE to 8,000 BCE). The extinction is believed to have been caused by two factors. The first was natural climate change on a global scale, specifically the end of the last glacial period, known popularly as the last ice age. Technically speaking, we’re still in an ice age, one that has lasted millions of years — we’re just in an interglacial period at the moment. At the time of the Quaternary extinction, the warming of the planet and retreating glaciers put many species at risk. Large animals that had evolved for cold weather died out, and those that survived fell prey to humans invading their environment”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Europe’s Colonization of Asia&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In July of 1405, a Chinese fleet under the command of Zheng He departed from Suzhou for a tour around the Pacific Ocean. The scale of the expedition was massive. Over three hundred ships, almost twenty-eight thousand crewmen, mostly military. They visited much of Southeast Asia, including Brunei, Java, and Thailand. They stopped in India, the Horn of Africa, and Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China in 1405 was home to sixty-five million people. England had only two million. China was the largest economy in the world at that time. India was second. And the Chinese fleets were much more advanced than those of any European power. Their largest ship was four hundred feet long and had a four-tiered deck. By comparison, Christopher Columbus’s largest ship, the Santa María, was roughly fifty-eight feet long.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More about author: &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Work Rules! by Laszlo Bock</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/work-rules.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-07-11:/blog/work-rules.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;Insights from Inside Google That Will Transform How You Live and Lead by Laszlo Bock&lt;/q&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work Rules! is an informative look at Google’s people management. After reading it, I am still not entirely convinced that Google’s approach is applicable to every company but the lessons below certainly are …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;Insights from Inside Google That Will Transform How You Live and Lead by Laszlo Bock&lt;/q&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work Rules! is an informative look at Google’s people management. After reading it, I am still not entirely convinced that Google’s approach is applicable to every company but the lessons below certainly are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*HLDCRwhxgRYIWA4-xvHTBQ.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*HLDCRwhxgRYIWA4-xvHTBQ.png.png" alt="Work Rules cover" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Culture &amp;gt; strategy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give people slightly more trust, freedom, and authority than you are comfortable with. If leaders aren’t nervous, they haven’t provided enough space for employees to surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hiring&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every company has limited resources. Take the time to hire only the best. Hire only those better than you in a meaningful way. Do not let managers make hiring decision for their teams — assess candidates objectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Finding the best talent&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get the best referrals and be very specific in defining requirements. Make recruiting everyone’s job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Empowering employees&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliminate status symbols. Make data-driven decision. Have high expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Performance management&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the time to set goals correctly. Gather peer feedback and use a calibration process to finalize rating. Split rewards and development conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Build a learning institution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have the best people teach and place them under a microscope. Apply how your best people operate broadly. Invest only in education that provably changes people’s behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Pay unfairly&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wide variations in pay are necessary to reflect the power law of performance. Emphasize accomplishment, not compensation. Reward failure when well thought out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also published on &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>1984 by George Orwell</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/1984.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-06-13:/blog/1984.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;George Orwell‘s 1984 (published in 1949) is clearly influenced by Ayn Rand’s The Fountainhead (published in 1943). Along with Atlas Shrugged published in the 1957 at the height of the Cold War these books compose an intellectual series describing the tragic consequences the western world would experience if …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;George Orwell‘s 1984 (published in 1949) is clearly influenced by Ayn Rand’s The Fountainhead (published in 1943). Along with Atlas Shrugged published in the 1957 at the height of the Cold War these books compose an intellectual series describing the tragic consequences the western world would experience if Communism (or more broadly Totalitarianism) are allowed to spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*7CUVpzNZEgjnPfZ2Vvp5kw.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*7CUVpzNZEgjnPfZ2Vvp5kw.png.png" alt="Book cover: 1984 by George Orwell" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Totalitarian regimes discourage rational thought&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“War is peace. Freedom is slavery. Ignorance is strength”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the key slogans of the totalitarian Party in Orwell’s 1984. People opposing such absurd slogans are considered traitors. By enforcing the propagation of such slogans, the totalitarian regime ensures that no decision it makes can be judged on the basis of reason. This ensures the Party’s preservation because there is no remaining tool to oppose the poorly run society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Who controls the past controls the future&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orwell takes the popular saying that history is written by winners to an extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Who controls the past controls the future. Who controls the present controls the past.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totalitarians convince the general population that their lives are better today by rewriting history, and therefore securing the regime’s future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And when memory failed and written records were falsified — when that happened, the claim of the Party to have improved the conditions of human life had got to be accepted, because there did not exist, and never again could exist, any standard against which it could be tested.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;q&gt;Author site &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Platform Revolution by Parker, Alstyne, and Choudary</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/platform-revolution.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-05-30:/blog/platform-revolution.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Below are some of my takeaways from the book Platform Revolution: How Networked Markets Are Transforming the Economy — and How to Make Them Work for You by Geoffrey Parker, Marshall Van Alstyne, and Sangeet Paul Choudary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was written in 2016 at what I would call the height of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Below are some of my takeaways from the book Platform Revolution: How Networked Markets Are Transforming the Economy — and How to Make Them Work for You by Geoffrey Parker, Marshall Van Alstyne, and Sangeet Paul Choudary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was written in 2016 at what I would call the height of the platform optimism. It’s fascinating to read the book in 2020 when the pure-platform companies are still yet to make money (Uber, Lyft) and some might never make money (&lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2020-softbank-heads-for-record-loss/" target="_blank"&gt;WeWork&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*Pru4vGiSjBL6wD2y6r89Xg.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*Pru4vGiSjBL6wD2y6r89Xg.png.png" alt="Cover: Platform Revolution: How Networked Markets Are Transforming the Economy — and How to Make Them Work for You by Geoffrey Parker, Marshall Van Alstyne, and Sangeet Paul Choudary" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Platform purpose: facilitate matches between producers and consumers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Supply economies of scale were the propulsion of modern traditional industries. Network effects, on the other hand, are demand economies of scale which generate the value of today’s platforms&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Platforms should be designed around the core interaction of participants, value unit, and filter. Key functions: pull, facilitate, match&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Governance: need to prevent market failures such as information asymmetry, externalities, monopoly power, and risk&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Key metrics should explain liquidity, matching and trust. Examples are relative size of various user bases, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Customer_lifetime_value" target="_blank"&gt;lifetime value&lt;/a&gt; of producers and consumers, sales conversion&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Strategies to capture value: prevent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-sided_market#Multihoming" target="_blank"&gt;multihoming&lt;/a&gt;, foster innovation then monetize,&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-sided_market#Threat_of_envelopment" target="_blank"&gt; platform envelopment&lt;/a&gt;, leverage value of information (advertising)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Author website: &lt;a href="https://adamnovotny.com" target="_blank"&gt;adamnovotny.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>The Billionaire Raj by James Crabtree</title><link href="https://adamnovotny.com/blog/the-billionaire-raj.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Adam Novotny</name></author><id>tag:adamnovotny.com,2020-05-03:/blog/the-billionaire-raj.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The only bright spot of the current &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2019%E2%80%9320_coronavirus_pandemic" target="_blank"&gt;COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; pandemic is the time I have to read. After finishing the excellent book The Billionaire Raj by James Crabtree, I decided to list 3 takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*MFiM4S9wpv5_0SnPpV4VVQ.jpeg.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*MFiM4S9wpv5_0SnPpV4VVQ.jpeg.png" alt="The Billionaire Raj cover by James Crabtree" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Socialism is evil&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from an ex-communist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czechoslovakia" target="_blank"&gt;Czechoslovakia&lt;/a&gt; (now split into &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_Republic" target="_blank"&gt;Czech Republic&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slovakia" target="_blank"&gt;Slovakia&lt;/a&gt;) I …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The only bright spot of the current &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2019%E2%80%9320_coronavirus_pandemic" target="_blank"&gt;COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; pandemic is the time I have to read. After finishing the excellent book The Billionaire Raj by James Crabtree, I decided to list 3 takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*MFiM4S9wpv5_0SnPpV4VVQ.jpeg.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*MFiM4S9wpv5_0SnPpV4VVQ.jpeg.png" alt="The Billionaire Raj cover by James Crabtree" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Socialism is evil&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from an ex-communist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czechoslovakia" target="_blank"&gt;Czechoslovakia&lt;/a&gt; (now split into &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_Republic" target="_blank"&gt;Czech Republic&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slovakia" target="_blank"&gt;Slovakia&lt;/a&gt;) I have strong views about the dark sides of socialism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Billionaire Raj covers the socialist darkness in India in the first half of the book. The description is always the same for every country: chronic shortages, economic stagnation, lack of freedom, red tape...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time people are not allowed to compete for profit, they find other competitions: power or who can get away with more bribes. It takes two generations for a country to recover from the damages of socialism: first to learn to live in a market-based economy, and the second to forget about the scars. India as well as many other countries is yet conclude the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. India has enormous, unfulfilled potential&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of India’s tailwinds is very long: large population, second largest &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_English-speaking_population" target="_blank"&gt;English speaking&lt;/a&gt; population in the world, excellent education, free elections and media, western-style government institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sporadically some of the these have manifested themselves: both the CEOs of Google &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sundar_Pichai" target="_blank"&gt;Sundar Pichai&lt;/a&gt; and Microsoft &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satya_Nadella" target="_blank"&gt;Satya Nadella&lt;/a&gt; grew up in India. But to the disappointment of the average person, these tend to be anecdotal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href="/theme/images/1*L8BlJ8as_ML7e9kyfsUmgg.png.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/theme/images/1*L8BlJ8as_ML7e9kyfsUmgg.png.png" alt="India vs China GDP per capita" style="width: 100%" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Corruption and the resource curse&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the book is spent on personal stories of billionaires who achieved great wealth by gaining monopoly status in their industries through shady connections with politicians (some voluntary, some not). Innovation grinds to a halt when 90% of 50 largest companies are conglomerates, which raise all risk-capital banks are able to lend due to their relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Crabtree describes Mukesh Ambani, Vijay Mallya and other examples but their rise to power is always the same and differs only in the type of industry they dominate. In the 1990s, only two Indians made Forbes list of the world’s wealthiest. Now, there are over 100, behind only the United States, China and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of India’s economy is a form of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_curse" target="_blank"&gt;resource curse&lt;/a&gt;. Even basic businesses such as the making of alcoholic drinks can make a business person one of the world’s richest simply by dominating the entire country. This doesn’t exist in small countries so entrepreneurs have to innovate. There is no point in growing further if you’re already a big fish in a small pond.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry></feed>